A Guide to the Papers of Floyd E. Johnson 1938-1994
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Floyd E. Johnson 1938-1994
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11765,-a
This collection consists of approximately 12,075 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by the Floyd E. Johnson estate on March 1, 2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
Floyd E. Johnson was educated at Lane High School, Charlottesville, Virginia, 1925-1929, the University of Virginia (B.S. in Architecture), 1929-1934, and the University of Virginia Graduate School, Instructor in Art and Architectural Design, 1934-1935. He was the son of Willelma Vest Johnson and Mary Hiserman Johnson, and married Anne Herron Johnson while working as a draftsman for a local firm.
During his war service, Johnson served in the United States Navy Reserves, June 1, 1943-January 12, 1946, serving as a Recognition Instructor, Recognition School, Columbus, Ohio, and a Gunnery Instructor, Naval Aerial Gunnery School, Purcell, Oklahoma, earning an Asiatic-Pacific Area Campaign ribbon, an American Area Campaign ribbon, Expert Rifle Medal, Letter of Commendation from U.S. Army in Hawaiian Area and the World War II Victory ribbon.
His early architectural experience was as an Associate with Milton Grigg, 1935-1938; Partner, Grigg & Johnson, 1938-1940; Architect, Floyd E. Johnson, 1940-1942; and Architect for Slaughter, Savile & Blackburn, Newport News, Army and Navy Projects.
After the war, Johnson worked by himself for a year, 1946-1947; as an Instructor for the School of Architecture, University of Virginia, 1947-1950; a Partner, Johnson, Craven & Gibson, Architects, 1947- 1987; and Principal, Johnson, Craven & Gibson, Inc., Architects, 1987-1994. David Jameson Gibson and Thomas Whitmore Stuart Craven, (1917-1989), were also University of Virginia architecture graduates, Gibson in 1937 and Craven in 1941. After he sold his interest in the firm, Johnson continued his architectural work as a consultant.
Johnson became a member of the American Institute of Architects in 1939, and was elected to the College of Fellows of the American Institute of Architects in 1970, a lifetime honor recognizing outstanding contribution to the profession. He has also received the Arthur Ross Classical America Award for life-long devotion to the classical tradition.
Locally, Johnson served on the Albemarle Planning Commission, 1947-1968, and helped rewrite the county's zoning ordinance. For over fifty years, Johnson worked with the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation on numerous restoration projects to preserve historic Monticello. He has also served as Chairman of the Virginia Fine Arts Commission. In 1989, Johnson received the Raven Society Award for high scholastic achievement and service to the University of Virginia and the First Lifetime Achievement Award for outstanding service in preservation by the Thomas Jefferson Branch of the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities in 1994.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists primarily of architectural drawings, plans, and renderings, and photographs, slides, correspondence, and papers related to the architectural work by architect Floyd E. Johnson (1909- 1999), Charlottesville, Virginia, ca. 12,075 total items (28 Hollinger boxes and 100 oversize folders, containing 2,275 drawings), ca. 1910-1999, for projects chiefly in Albemarle County and other Virginia locations. Among the projects were the restoration of Monticello and Shadwell, various buildings at the University of Virginia, numerous original designs for private residences such as Cherry Hill, and restoration of residences, such as that for Glen Echo, Belle Grove, and his own home, the Glendower Mill House.
Index to Projects
Airport Terminal Building, Charlottesville, Virginia (OS Tray 258)
Albemarle County Courthouse (Box 10; and OS Folders 23, 31)
Amvest Corporation (OS Folder 76)
Anderson, Mr. and Mrs. Richard, Residence, North Garden, Albermarle County, Virginia (Box 11)
Ash Lawn, Albermarle County, Virginia Proposal (Box 11)
Bath County Cooperative Library (OS Folder 23)
Bellair Plantation, Albemarle County, Virginia (Box 20)
Belle Grove, Scottsville, Virginia, for Sykes Scherman, also see under Valmont (Boxes 1, 8, 9, 11, 20, 28; and OS Folders 27, 32)
Bicentennial Center for Piedmont Virginia Community College Alterations and Additions, Dedication (Box 7)
Blair House Restaurant (OS Folder 23)
Boar's Head Inn, Charlottesville, Virginia (Boxes 1, 11)
Brookwood School, Thomasville, Georgia (Boxes 1, 25; and OS Folder 33)
Buchardt, William, House, Post Oak, Virginia (Boxes 11; OS Folder 33)
Burning Daylight Farm, Albemarle County, Virginia, for Mr. and Mrs. Arthur A. Watson, Jr. (Boxes 1, 7, 11, 12; and OS Folders 7, 23 35, 36, 92)
Butterfield, W.S. Servant's House (OS Folder 24)
Capitol Square, Richmond, Virginia (Box 12)
Castle Hill, [Albemarle County, Virginia] (OS Folder 37)
Charlottesville Courthouse, Charlottesville, Virginia (OS Folder 37)
Cherry Hill Estate, Albemarle County, Virginia, for Mr. and Mrs. Alonzo Rinehart (Boxes 7, 12, 25; and OS Folder 8, 38)
Christmas Hill Club House, Albemarle County, Virginia (OS Folder 24)
Christ Church, Glendower, St. Anne's Parish, Albemarle County, Virginia (Boxes 7, 12; and OS folders 24, 39)
"Chub Cay" House and Hotel, The Berry's Island Group, Bahamas (OS Folder 40)
Cismont Manor Farm, Keswick, Virginia, for Mr. and Mrs. Kenneth Wheeler (Boxes 1, 8, 12; and OS Folders 24, 41)
Cocke's Mill House, North Garden, Albemarle County, Virginia, for Dr. David L. Morris (Boxes 1, 8, under Morris, Box 9, 13)
Crozet Library, Crozet, Virginia (Boxes 7, 14 under Jefferson-Madison Regional Library - Crozet, 25)
Daily Progress Complex Alterations (OS Folder 14)
Derwent, Powhatan County, Virginia (Boxes 8, 13; and OS folders 8, 42)
Dodson, Mr. and Mrs. Truman, House (OS Folder 14)
Donegal Alterations for Mr. and Mrs. Pierson Scott (OS Folder 14)
Echo Brook Farm, Keswick, Virginia (OS Folder 43)
Edgemont, Albemarle County, Virginia (Boxes 8, 21; and OS Folder 92)
Ednam Forest Studies (OS Folder 14) and Proposed Apartments (OS Tray 258)
Esmont Farm, Albemarle County, Virginia (Box 21)
Fairfax Hall, Waynesboro, Virginia (Boxes 8, 13)
Faulconer, W.H., Garage, Scottsville, Virginia (OS Folder 76)
Ferry, George B., Real Estate (OS Folder 24)
Fluvanna County Courts and Public Facilities Proposal (Box 13)
Fuller, W.W., Proposed Motor Court, Albemarle County, Virginia (OS Folder 45)
Gallison Hall, for James F. Scott (Box 13)
Gibben's Farm Building, Fauquier County, Virginia, for Mr. and Mrs. Wayne Gibbens (Boxes 1, 9; and OS Folder 46)
Glen Echo Farm, Albemarle County, Virginia for Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Watson (Boxes 2, 7, 13, 14, 25; and OS Folders 25, 47, 48)
Glendower, Albemarle County, Virginia, for Mr. and Mrs. Alfred E. Jackson (Boxes 7, 25; and OS Folders 25, 29, 50, 87)
Goodall, Wayne (Box 14)
Gristmill Square, Warm Springs, Virginia, for Mr. and Mrs. Philip Hirsch (OS Folder 52)
Hatton Ferry, Scottsville, Virginia (Boxes 2, 14, 21; and OS Folder 52)
Hennage House, Williamsburg, Virginia, for Mr. and Mrs. Joseph H. Hennage (OS Folders 10, 51, 88)
Herdeg, John A. Residence, Mendenhall, Chester County, Pennsylvania (also known as William Peters House) (Boxes 2, 9, 14; and OS Folder 11)
The Hermitage, Buckingham County, Virginia, for James L. Brown (Box 11; and OS Folders 13, 52)
Hjorth, Mr. and Mrs. John T., Carter's Bridge, Virginia, Porch (OS Folder 25)
Hollymead Renovation (Box 9 and OS Tray 258)
Horseshoe Farm, Albemarle County, Virginia, for Mrs. Harlod B. Alexander (Box 14; and OS Folders 12, 52)
Humpback Rocks, Blue Ridge Parkway, Proposed Lodge and Store (OS Folder 76)
Indian Trace Farm, Locust Dale, Virginia, for Mr. and Mrs. Stephen Murphy (OS Folders 13, 52)
Ingleside Farm, Residence for Bill and Jana Crutchfield, Albemarle County, Virginia (OS Folder 52)
Jackson, Dr. A.E. Memorial, at Glendower Church, Scottsville, Virginia (Box 2; and OS Folder 13)
Janssen, Alex and Pat, Residence, Albemarle County, Virginia (Boxes 9, 14; OS Folder 13)
Jefferson Mill Addition, for Dr. and Mrs. James L. Camp III (Boxes 9, 14; and OS Folder 54)
Jefferson-Madison Regional Library (OS Folder 55)
Jennings, Mr. and Mrs. M.C., Residence, Columbus, Georgia (OS Folder 26)
Johnson, Mary Stuart, daughter of Floyd Johnson - Memorial, Albemarle County, Virginia (OS Folders 84, 93)
Joint Security Complex for Charlottesville and Albemarle County, Virginia (OS Tray 258)
Lafayette Hill Tavern, Fluvanna County, Virginia, Topographical Map, for Mr. and Mrs. John Graham (OS Folder 76)
Lanigan & Associates, Thomasville, Georgia (Boxes 2, 9, 14; and OS Folders 26, 76, 92)
Levy Opera House, Charlottesville, Virginia (Box 9)
Lewis, Mr. and Mrs. James L. Residence (OS Folder 76)
Long Branch, Millwood, Clark County, Virginia, for Harry Z. Isaacs and [Caj?] Haakausson (Box 22; and OS Folder 78)
Madison County Courthouse, for John M. Powell, Clerk (Boxes 2, 14; and OS Folders 26, 59)
McConnell, James H.T., Jr. Residence, Rapidan, Orange County, Virginia (Boxes 2, 9, 15; and OS Folders 26,56)
McIntire Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, Renovations for the Albemarle County Historial Society (Boxes 2, 15; and OS Folder 57)
McIntyre House (OS Tray 258)
Mahan, O. Leland, Residence, Leesburg, Virginia (Box 15)
Marcy, Dr. M. Farmington House, Albemarle County, Virginia (OS Folder 24)
Martha Jefferson Hospital and Sanitorium, Inc. Alterations and Additions (Box 15)
Mill House, Scottsville, Virginia, for Mr. and Mrs. Floyd E. Johnson (Boxes 7, and 8 under Dwyer Miller House, 15; and OS Folder 58)
Mirador, Greenwood, Albemarle County, Virginia, for John Burghardt (Boxes 2, 15; and OS Folders 60, 61, 62, 89)
Miyagawa, Captain and Mrs. Robert, Residence, Shores, Virginia (Box 15)
Monticello, Albemarle County, Virginia, Restorations, etc. for the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation (Boxes 3, 7, 8, 15, 16, 17, 22, 25, 28; and OS Folders 15, 16, 26, 63 through 74, 90, 91; and OS Tray 258)
Monticola, Albemarle County, Virginia, Residence Alterations and Additions for Cynthia Littlejohn and Edward Silverman (Boxes 3, 9, 17; and OS Folder 16)
Montpelier, Orange County, Virginia, Viewing Stand, etc (Box 17; and OS Folder 76)
Mount Ida, Albemarle County, Virginia, for James Brady Murray, Jr. who had it moved from Buckingham County (Boxes 3, 9, 17; and OS Folders 26, 75)
Mount Moriah Methodist Church (OS Folder 26)
Moyer House, Crozet, Virginia, for Mr. and Mrs. Richard W. Moyer (Box 17)
Oakencroft Farm, Albemarle County, Virginia, Residence for Mr. and Mrs. John B. Rogan (OS Tray 259)
Oldtown Farm Residence Alterations and Additions, Point Pleasant, West Virginia, for Charles C. Lewis (Box 2, under Lewis, and Boxes 8, 17; OS Folder 79)
Peaks of Otter Lodge and Restaurant, Blue Ridge Parkway (Boxes 8, 17)
People's National Bank Loan Department (OS Folder 14); Elkton Branch (OS Folder 27)
Perkins, W.A., Jr., Residence, Deltaville, Virginia (OS Folder 93)
Petty, Mr. and Mrs. H.L., Residence, Albemarle County, Virginia (OS Folder 27; and OS Tray 259)
Piedmont Virginia Community College (Boxes 9, 17, 28; and OS Folders 14, 27, 92; and Tray 259)
Plain Dealing Farm, Keene, Virginia, for Philippe de Villegas (Boxes 4, 17, 23)
Plumb House and Property, Waynesboro, Virginia (Box 17)
Poindexter House, Waynesboro, Virginia, for Mr. and Mrs. Gordon W. Poindexter, Jr. (Box 17; and OS Folder 76)
Powhatan Plantation, King George County, Virginia, for Caroline Guest (Boxes 4, 9, 17)
Rockefeller Residence and Conservatory, Albemarle County, Virginia, for Dori Rockefeller (Box 18)
Round Hill Alterations and Additions for Mr. and Mrs. William O. Bourke (Box 18)
St. James Church Proposed Design (OS Tray 259)
St. John's Church, Scottsville, Virginia (OS Folder 27)
St. Luke's Episcopal Church, Powhatan County, Virginia, Alterations and Additions (Box 4; and OS Folder 80)
Scottsville Museum, Scottsville, Virginia (OS Folder 77)
Scottsville Water Facility Improvement (OS Folder 27)
Semmes, Mr. and Mrs. S.P., House (OS Folder 27)
Shadwell, Albemarle County, Virginia, Restoration (Boxes 4, 9, 18, 24; and OS Folders 16, 81, 94)
Sherwood Hill, Harrisonburg, Virginia, Residence for Mr. and Mrs. Robert Frazier (Boxes 4, 13; OS Folder 44)
State Capitol Area, Richmond, Virginia (OS Folder 16, 93)
State Farm Mutual Automobile Insurance Company (OS Tray 259)
Stevens, Mr. and Mrs. residence, Bellair, Albemarle County, Virginia (OS Folder 28)
Stonewall Jackson House, Lexington, Virginia (Boxes 9, 18, 28)
Stuart Cemetary and Stuart Manor Farm, Lewisburg, West Virginia, for Mrs. Turner Rust Ratrie (Boxes 9, 18)
Swan House, Atlanta, Georgia (Box 24)
Tallwood, Albemarle County, Virginia, for Peggy Van Clief (Box 18; and OS Folder 77)
Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation Projects - Lighting for Liberty Bell Replica at the Charlottesville Fire House on Ridge Street (Box 18; and OS Folder 92) and Visitor's Center (Boxes 18, 19; also under Monticello in OS drawings)
Tri-County Riding Club (Box 19; and OS Folder 77)
Tuckahoe Plantation, near Richmond, Virginia (Box 19)
Tufton Barn (OS Folder 16)
United States Capitol (Box 24)
University of Virginia - photographs (Box 9) general projects (Box 19) research (Box 24)
University of Virginia - Clinch Valley College Academic Building (OS Folder 30)
University of Virginia - Dormitories, Proposed (OS Tray 259)
University of Virginia - East Range (Box 19)
University of Virginia - Faulkner House (OS Folder 9)
University of Virginia - Garden Pavilions Restoration (OS Folder 97)
University of Virginia - Lawn Improvement (Box 19)
University of Virginia - Madison Hall Renovation Phase II (Box 19; and OS Folder 97; and OS Tray 259)
University of Virginia - Miller Center (Boxes 4, 19; and OS Folder 30, 97)
University of Virginia - Newcomb Hall (OS Folder 30)
University of Virginia - North Grounds Landscape Committee (Box 20)
University of Virginia - Rotunda Esplanade Renovation (Box 20) research (Box 24) and drawings (OS Folder 95, 96)
Viewmont, Albemarle County, Virginia (Box 9)
Virginia National Bank, Charlottesville, Virginia (OS Folder 28, 77; and OS Tray 259)
Virginia Stage Lines, Inc. Terminal Building, Charlottesville, Virginia (OS Folder 28)
Waterford, Loudoun County, Virginia (Box 24)
Western Virginia Bicentennial Information Center, Albemarle County, Virginia (OS Folder 82; and OS Tray 259)
Westminster Presbyterian Church, Sunday School Building, Charlottesville, Virginia (OS Folder 28)
Whippoorwill Farm, Albemarle County, Virginia, for Dr. and Mrs. Douglas Nicoll (Box 20)
White Hall Farm, Gloucester, Virginia, for Mr. and Mrs. Peter Hunt (Boxes 4, 20; and OS Folder 17, 29, 83, 98, 99)
Wiley, Gordon, Shop Front, Charlottesville, Virginia (OS Folder 28)
Wilkins, Edward B. Residence, Charlottesville, Virginia (OS Folder 77)
William and Mary, College of, President's House (OS Folder 29)
Williamsburg, Virginia - photographs (Box 9) research (Box 24) survery of Revolutionary War cemetary and buildings (OS Folder 29, 100)
Woodberry Forest School Auditorium, Orange County, Virginia (OS Folder 29)
Corporation (OS Folder 76)
Contents List
- Series I: Papers of Floyd E. Johnson 1953-1999
  - Correspondence: Albemarle County Courthouse Portrait Committee 1954-1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: American Insitute of Architects 1966, 1970-1994, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Architectural Advisory Board of Legislative Process 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Bailey Printing, Inc - Receipts 1991 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Belle Grove, Scottsville, Virginia 1979-1985 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Boar's Head Inn Test of Time Award to Thomas Craven 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Brookwood School, Thomasville, Georgia 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Burning Daylight Farm 1987-1995 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Cismont Manor Farm, Mr. and Mrs. Kenneth Wheeler 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Cocke's Mill House, David L. Morris 1989 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Thomas W. S. Craven, including the Award for the Design of the Boar's Head Inn 1974-1975, 1988-1991 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Ednam Village, Mr. and Mrs. K. K. Knickerbocker 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: F.A. Bartlett Tree Company 1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Gibben's Farm Building 1989-1993 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Glen Echo 1987-1992 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: H. Brice Graves 1953-1954 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Hatton Ferry Committee 1983-1989 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: John A. Herdeg 1992 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Edward Hillenbrand, Furniture Maker 1986 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Jackson Memorial, Glendower Church 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Jefferson Mill 1972 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Andy Johnson, Final Site Plan 1990 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Johnson Bench copyright 1975, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Johnson, Craven, and Gibson Architects 1972-1989 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: A.E. Kendrew 1952-1963, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Lanigan and Associates 1983-1990 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Charles C. Lewis 1983-1986 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Alfred Locke 1989 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Madison County Courthouse - John M. Powell 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: McConnell Residence 1991-1993 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: McIntire Library Renovation 1992-1994 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Mirador - Kennel, for Paul Burghardt 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous Business 1933-1973 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous Business - Carbon Copies 1952-1958 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Monticello 1970-1993, n.d., 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Monticello Dome Room 1982-1990 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Monticello Dome Room - Stolzle-Oberglas 1984-1989 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Monticola 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Mt. Ida 1997 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: National Council of Architectural Registration Boards, with forms 1983 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Personal 1955-1994, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Plain Dealing Farm 1990 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Powhatan Plantation - Caroline Guest 1994 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Randolph Building 1989-1992 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: St. Luke's Episcopal Church 1995-1996 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Shadwell 1954-1995 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Shadwell-Michie (Draft and Copy of Plans) 1960 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Sherwood Hill - Mr. and Mrs. Robert Y. Frazier 1993 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Smith and Garrett Architects 1991-1996 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation 1985-1986 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: University of Virginia Miller Center 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: University of Virginia School of Architecture 1986-1990 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: White Hall Farm 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: William P. Welsh 1954-1955 (Box 4)
  - Personal - Architectural Advisory Board of Legislative Process Commission 1973-1974 (Box 5)
    Re: the State Capitol Building
  - Personal - Awards, Citations, Certificates, etc. of Floyd Johnson 1932-1998 (Box 5)
  - Personal - Calendars and Planners 1964, 1971-1981, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Personal - Fishing - Annual Marlin Trip 1974-1984, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Personal - Game and Wildlife 1982, 1988-1993 (Box 5)
  - Personal - Liability for Architects 1988-1990 (Box 5)
  - Personal - Maps 1973, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Personal - Miscellaneous ca. 1950-1989, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Personal - Naval Service Information 1942-1953 (Box 5)
  - Personal - The Raven Society 1988-1998 (Box 6)
  - Personal - Redland Club 1965-1974 (Box 6)
  - Personal - Registration to Practice Architecture in West Virginia 1976-1990 (Box 6)
  - Personal - Scottsville Planning Commission, the Civic League, the State Art Commission, Albemarle Planning Commission, etc. 1955-1972, 1989 (Box 6)
  - Personal - Shooting and Guns 1943-1966 (Box 6)
  - Personal - Virginia Society of the American Institute of Architects Honors Committee 1985-1994 (Box 6)
  - Personal - Virginia Society of the American Institue of Architects Honors Committee Proposal to Honor the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation 1988 (Box 6)
  - Photographs - Bicentennial Center for Piedmont Virginia Community College ca. 1974-1981 (Box 7)
    Alterations and Additions and Dedication (Negatives)
  - Photographs - Burning Daylight Farm 1988, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Photographs - Charlottesville, Virginia ca. 1910-1974, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Photographs - Cherry Hill Farm, Albemarle County 1991, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Photographs - Churches ca. 1960-1999, n.d. (Box 7)
    Including: Episcopal Church, Remington, Virginia; St. John's Church, St. Anne's Parish; Christ Church, Glendower; Church of Our Savior, Old Stone Chapel; Entrance Door Hinge for Sacred Heart Catholic Church, Covington, Virginia
  - Photographs - Crozet Library n.d. (Box 7)
  - Photographs - Details ca. 1975-1996, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Photographs - Glen Echo ca. 1987-1989, n.d., also oversize - see OS Folder 25 (Box 7)
  - Photographs - Glendower 1995-1999, n.d., also oversize - see OS Folder 25 (Box 7)
  - Photographs - Log Cabins and Related Structures 1975, 1988, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Photographs - Mill House, [Scottsville, Virginia] 1995-1996, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Photographs - Miscellaneous (Unidentified) 1995-1998, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Photographs - Monticello 1974-1986 (Box 7)
  - Photographs - Monticello ca. 1987-1989, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Photographs - Old Town Farm 1984-1985, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Photographs - Peaks of Otter Lodge and Restaurant 1962-1964 (Box 8)
  - Photographs - Personal ca. 1929-1999, n.d., 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Photographs - Personal - Hunting ca. 1995-1999, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Photographs - Personal (Negatives) 1995, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Photographs - Vacations 1962-1998, n.d., 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Photographs - Renderings and Models 1979-1990, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Photographs - Residences and Other Buildings - B 1961-1980, n.d. (Box 8)
    Including Belle Grove, Bowers Residence, and Buckhardt White Post House
  - Photographs - Residences and Other Buildings - C-F 1936-1990, n.d. (Box 8)
    Including Cismont Manor, Cloverfield's, Cocke's Mill House, Derwent, Donegal Cottage, Dwyer's Miller House, Edgemont, and Fairfax Hall
  - Photographs - Residences and Other Buildings - G-L 1974-1979, n.d. (Box 9)
    Including Glens Farm Building and Stables, Hollymead, Stonewall Jackson House, Alex and Pat Janssen Residence, the Thomas Jefferson Memorial, Lanigan and Associates Office Building, Thomasville, Georgia, and Levy Opera House
  - Photographs - Residences and Other Buildings - M-P 1984-1996, n.d. (Box 9)
    Including McConnell Garden Symposium and Pool, Melpar Inc., Monticola, Morris House, Mount Ida, [Overseer's?] House, William Peters House, Piedmont Virginia Community College (also oversize - see OS Folder 14), Plymouth Federal Savings and Loan Association Building, and Powhatan Plantation
  - Photographs - Residences and Other Buildings - R-Z 1999, n.d. (Box 9)
    Including Ridge Street Houses, Pierson Scott Tobacco Barn, Stuart Manor and Cemetary, Tainter addition, Thacker's Place, Valmont (Scott House), Viewmont, Virginia National Bank, Wall House, Boyd, Maryland, Waterford, White Marsh, and Yorktown First Custom House in America
  - Photographs - Residences and Other Buildings - Unidentified ca. 1960-1999, n.d., 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Photographs - Residences and Other Buildings - Unidentified Holsinger n.d. (Box 9)
  - Photographs - Residences and Other Buildings - Unidentified Negatives n.d. (Box 9)
  - Photographs - Shadwell and Jefferson's Old Mill 1959, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Photographs - University of Virginia 1961-1980, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Photographs - Warrenton, Virginia n.d. (Box 9)
    Main Street Buildings